Hello, everyone. Welcome to the Computer-assisted theorem proving module. In this module, we'll
be mainly focusing on specific methods for proving theorems using computers, and that is called
interactive improving. And we will cover many, many parts of that. So in this video, I will
just introduce the topic to you. So I will try and give you a brief introduction of what
is interactive theorem proving, what are we doing over the next 10 weeks to study that topic,
and what do I expect you to already know. I will briefly discuss what concepts and techniques
I actually already know from previous modules, but I'll also briefly introduce different concepts
through the different weeks. So I make sure that you are refreshed, but I assume that you
have some background here. And lastly, I will organize some organizational notes regarding
this module and the coursework. So before I talk about interactive theorem, I want to
recap with you the concept of formal proof. So recall, like I wanted to recall with me
the following Aristotelian syllogism. So if we assume that all men are mortal and Aristotle is
a man, and Aristotle is a mortal, we can then conclude from one and two and the modus ponens
logical rule that Aristotle is also mortal. I hope we all agree that this is an unambiguously
correct proof. So what is that? What is a formal proof? So basically a formal proof,
formal mathematical proof is one where is a mathematical proof that is unambiguously
clear and unambiguously correct as the syllogism that I just told you. So there is no doubt about
any gaps in the proof. So the goal here is to construct formal proofs of correctness
for mathematical theorems and for algorithm systems. So basically we want to construct proofs
at the same level of correctness as this Aristotelian syllogism, but for real,
for interesting mathematical theorems or for interesting computer systems. So why is that
interesting? It's because basically formal proofs are the closest thing to objectively
and unambiguously correct proofs. And by that I mean the same level that we have seen with
that syllogism. So if you want to make that a bit more precise, what I mean by that is
that we want definitions and theorem statements, whose meaning and well formness are unambiguously
correct. And the proofs also have to be correct. And what that means is that the proofs have
to be performed with respect to precisely and concisely stated mathematical axioms.
And everything, you derive everything or all the mathematical proofs from those
precise and concise set of mathematical axioms. So in order for us to do that, we have to write
proofs and definitions in a formal language whose meaning is defined by a set of axioms.
Like for example, there are many types of axioms, like for example in your temporal logic.
For those of you who did the formal verification module with Hannah Schockler,
you will have seen what in general logic is. But there are also other types of axioms that
are more general and cover more things. Like for example, Zemirofrankel set theory. So this is a
set of axioms that you can use to build the entirety of mathematics. And there are many other
types of such axioms. And in this module, we primarily focus on higher order logic as a
set of axioms for proving mathematics. So the initial reason to bother with formal proofs
which is still very, very relevant until now is to, was like the initial reason was to
so-called formalize mathematics. And the first person to try and do that in fact was Euclid in
his Euclid's Elements book. And then later on, more than 100 years ago, Rosson Whitehead also
tried to do that. And what that means is they tried to reach formal proofs in the sense that
I just described in the previous slide, but for mathematics in general, or for summaries
of mathematics. Like for example, Euclid did it just for geometry. But historically, this
has been impossible because constructing a formal proof which is as unambiguous and as correct as
the Aristotelian syllogism, but for a real mathematical theorem is completely infeasible
to do it by hand. However, in the later part of the 20th century, electronic computers were
invented and this made it actually possible for us to construct formal mathematical proofs.
So there is a number of examples of interesting formal mathematical proofs that were constructed
by computers in the second half of the 20th century. And in this approach where you use an
electronic computer to generate the formal proofs, the idea is a somewhat straightforward idea. So you
have a very simple computer program to check every step in the proof, and then you have another
program to construct all the steps of the proof. So you have two computer programs, one to construct
the proof and another one to check the proof. And the program that checks the proof is called
the logical kernel, and the correctness of the whole formal proof would depend only on
the correctness of the logical kernel, which is the program that checks the proof.
And because the logical kernel is usually very simple, we can have high trust in the correctness
of the proofs. So now let's be a bit more practical. What is interactively improving?
So interactively improving is done using tools called interactively
improvers or proof-assistance. What are those? These are basically mechanized
or machine-based mathematical systems in which one specifies definitions and statements and proofs
in a formal language. And then the interactively improver makes sure that the proof only follows
from a specific set of actions. In our case, we will use the interactively improver,
Isabelle Hall. An example proof in that system is shown in the slide right in front of you.
So here we're proving that the square root of root is an irrational number. As shown here,
the user writes down the theorem in formal syntax of Isabelle, and then the user enters
high-level steps of the proof. And for example, you assume that you say, okay, let x is to be
the square root of two, and we assume that x is rational. And then we do a few steps,
and then we derive from that a contradiction. So this is a proof of irrationality of square root
of two. In mathematics, using interactively improvers, many, many formal proofs were
developed, especially in the last few years, and I would say why in a few slides.
So like the most recent and most interesting formal project is trying to generate a formal
mathematical proof from Fermat's last theorem. So this is currently an active project by Kevin
Buzzer Imperial College, but there are many other examples that I've seen here. But the
point of this slide is to say that interactively improvers are really becoming a practical way to
generate formal proofs, even for serious mathematical theorems. In computer science,
which I assume will be the interest of a majority of you, formal proof is used for
formal verification. So basically, we have a computer system, and so we write, we try to
describe that system in a language that's understood by an interactively improver,
and we try to describe its properties also that we want to verify. For example,
sorting algorithm sorts, or a search algorithm returns an element that finds whatever you're
searching for if it's in the database, something like that. So you specify a system and its
desired property is in a formal language. And this was also used to do a lot of landmark
verifications of computer systems. So interactively improvers were used to verify an entire
opening system kernel. Two compilers, and most recently, they've been adopted by industry very
heavily. So AWS used the improver Isabelle that we're studying here to formally verify
the mitral hypervisor, which is basically the hypervisor that AWS uses for all of its
virtual machines. And also Apple has used Isabelle to verify all of its cryptographic algorithms that
run on all the phones and on all the computers. So these are hyperlinks, you can actually check
the blog posts on both on Apple's website and on AWS website to see the scale of what you can
achieve using interactively improvers to verify real world systems. Now I talked about electronic
computers being invented, and that's already causing phone proofs to become practical. But in
the last few years, large language models, or foundation models in general, have even
made the use of interactively improvers even more practical. And in fact, they multiplied
the productivity of a user with the improver by an order of magnitude almost. We can now
automate so many parts of the process that it is very practical to verify
very large systems that would have been impossible two years ago.
So in fact, it's not, and in fact, LLMs did not only make the improving more feasible, but also
the improvers are making it possible for LLMs to learn mathematics because they can be used to
provide feedback for the LLM so that the LLM verifies its mathematical reasoning.
So if you have an LLM that's trying to prove a mathematical theorem, it can try to
give its proof to a theorem prover, interactively improver like Isabelle or something else,
and then it gets feedback from that theorem prover on whether its approach is correct or not.
And using that, the abilities of LLMs to do mathematics had dramatically improved
in the recent years. They have in fact achieved the International Math Olympiad
gold level performance, which was, which two years ago would have sounded like a complete,
a completely impossible goal. So now with LLMs and AI,
it's actually improving, is becoming a very practical tool that is used by a lot of
people in the industry. So, and a lot of mathematicians also, and a lot of computer
scientists in the research. So it's really, it's really a very practical tool at this point.
So my own research, I'm doing, I'm also using and developing and improving tools
within the ecosystem as well for my own research. So I primarily work on verifying algorithms for
verifying, formally verifying algorithms for AI. So this means that I build algorithms for AI and
then prove them correct using a theorem prover. I also sometimes do use them to just formalize
pure mathematical theorems or theorems from theorems from computer science,
for example, complexity theory. And more recently, I've been interested in AI for mathematics and
in basically developing AI based methods or LLM based methods to improve the practice of
fear improving using Isabelle or other interest improvers. And in fact, I have, if that
interests any of you, I have many dissertation topics for you, whether you do, if you want
like a master's project or a final year project, or if you want to do a summer internship or
something like that, I have or even a PhD, I have lots of project ideas. So if that topic,
that general topic interests you, please come and talk to me. So now let's talk about the actual
module structure and that we're going to do this this year. So we have a 10 week lecture period.
In the first five weeks, we'll be talking mainly about the foundations of fear improve,
interaction improving. So I'll be like introducing you to the basic syntax of the
theorem prover Isabelle, some basic proof concepts, and some basic, like, like, for example, mathematical
induction on numbers or other things. And I will then talk to you about ways Isabelle has
to automate proofs in order for you to not actually write all the steps to the proof
yourself. So Isabelle has automation itself. And then in the fifth week, I will talk
about to you about the more recent most recent advances and methods in integrating large language
models with Isabelle so that you can actually use that large language model to do a genetic
theorem proving, where you where you asked them where you asked them, we can do things
ranging from very simple things like asking the LLM, what is this syntax error explained to me
all the way up to tell it telling it to prove a very big theorem on its own.
So then in weeks from six to 10, we will actually talk about state of the art applications of
theorem provers within without AI in the areas of computer science and also in areas of
formal education. And sometimes we might also touch on mathematics. So basically,
the first half is basic is foundations, the second half of the module will be applications
improving that are all interesting, like that are advanced enough to be interesting.
So, as I told you, I expect you to have some background knowledge. This includes
mathematical induction, I expect you to know about that first order logic and how to formulate
statements in first order logic and basic functional programming. And as you would have done,
you would have had you have been exposed to these
concepts, whether it is in the foundations of computing modules, or programming,
for example, functional programming, you will have been exposed to it in the programming
practice and experiences module. But in any case, I will refresh these concepts with you as we build,
as we go through the through the module. So now let's go to the organizational points
of this module. So we will use the theorem prover is able whole, as I said, all these are hyperlinks,
so you can see what we're talking about, but they're also on keys. And, and on the course
website. So the so we use it is about the improver. And that, in order for you to ask
questions, you can ask them either on the key forum, or on the Isabelle zero community,
and I have added a link to that as well. This is like a very friendly community, please go
and ask people their questions about Isabelle that you have, especially if you're interested in if
you find this area interesting to go for, like, look, look, and you want to do further studies in
it, use the Isabelle zero as soon as possible, because an important thing is to get to know
the community. And we'll also use books. So there are three books or three documents that I
recommend you read them, not the whole thing, of course, like for every week, I'm saying what are
the obligatory reading, but in general, here, here, in this module, I'm expecting like, like,
there are there's obligatory reading. So like, for every week, there are some sections or some
chapters that you have to read from the in these books. So the books are all available online,
and these will be written on the keys in the course website as well. And the assessment will
be a formal, formal proof project, and an exam, it will be paper based. So so the coursework is
a practical part, and basically, the exam is a written part. Lastly, I want to discuss with you
the AI policy for this module. So during the group, it was large and small, I would
encourage you to not use LLMs, except in weeks one to four, I would encourage you to not use LLMs
except to just explain, to get an explanation of what an error is, a specific error. For example,
when you're trying to do something in Isabelle, you write something, then you get a syntax error,
and then you don't know what that means, or what that error means, then you copy and paste the
error to a web interface of an LLM, and then it tells you this error means so and so. This is how
you fix it. That's encouraged, like I would like you to do that, because that will accelerate your
learning. But I don't want you to do to have an AI system, solve the exercises that we're doing
in the large group or the small group tutorials, because this way, you will not learn the basics.
And if you don't learn the basics, you will not be able to use AI for doing more fun things.
And then week five onwards, during the larger group, small group tutorials, you can use AI
for more than just syntax error explanation. You can use it also to explain more mathematical
concepts, like mathematical concepts or mathematical proofs, or how to approach a problem
at a higher level than just syntax errors. For the coursework, there will be an AI policy
that will be part of the coursework, so please wait until then, and then you will see it.
And lastly, I would like to remind you that the exam will be 50% of the marks in this module,
and will be purely paper-based. So if you try to use AI for doing everything during these weeks,
my guess is that you will find it very hard to pass the exam.
So you need to actually understand the concepts yourself, because this will be paper-based.
That's all, and I hope you enjoy the course, and I'm looking forward to see you in the first group
tutorial.